Guide to the Aleksandr Kazem-Bek papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Aleksandr Kazem-Bek papers,
1930-1977.
Kazem-Bek, Aleksandr 1902-1977.
14.19 linear ft. (10 document boxes, 6 flat boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
BA#0528
7756884
The Aleksandr Kazem-Bek Papers consist of correspondence, family and personal documents, photographs, printed materials, lectures, notes, manuscripts, research materials, and drafts connected with Russian émigré social and political activist Aleksandr Kazem-Bek throughout his professional life.
Biographical Note
Aleksandr Kazem-Bek was born in Kazan on the 2nd (15th old style) of February, 1902, into an old noble family of Persian (Azeri) origin. He came from a line of distinguished academics and professors, the most notable of which, his paternal great grandfather, founded the Institute for Oriental Studies at the University of Kazan. As a child, Aleksandr often moved with his family throughout Europe, and lived for short periods of time in France, Italy, Switzerland, Germany, and Austria-Hungary. His family finally emigrated in February 1922, and eventually reached Belgrade through Constantinople with the White Army, which he had joined at the age of sixteen. It was during his years with the White Army that the young Kazem-Bek first showed his heroic and fiercely patriotic traits, which would characterize him in his future work as a social and political leader of the White Russian emigration.
In 1923, he moved to Munich, where he began his university studies. It was here that the youth movement called "Young Russia" was born. Kazem-Bek was its founder and leader throughout the 1920s and 1930s. Its members were given the name "Mladorossi," or "Young Russians," and their slogan was "Neither White nor Red, but Russian." The movement was disbanded in 1941.
Kazem-Bek moved to Paris in the mid-1920s, and obtained his doctorate in political and social sciences at the Institut d'Etudes Politiques de Paris. He worked for several years at a credit union in Monte Carlo, Monaco, until his return to Paris in 1929 as an established political activist of Europe's Russian émigré community. He was an active contributor to several notable émigré newspapers, such as Mladorosskaia iskra, the main publication of the Mladorossi. Because of his natural leadership abilities and his notable charisma, he succeeded in garnering continued support from various religious and political leaders.
In 1937, Kazem-Bek declared his resignation from the post of director of the Mladoross movement. In 1940, Aleksandr Kazem-Bek was arrested and imprisoned in a concentration camp. After his release, he and his family immigrated to the United States, where Kazem-Bek continued his work as social, political, and religious leader of the emigration. Among fulfilling other duties, he edited and regularly submitted to the San Francisco-based Russian émigré newspaper Novaia Zaria, and occasionally delivered sermons at the St. Nicholas Cathedral in New York City.
While in San Francisco, Kazem-Bek was also actively involved in the distribution of literature to Russian prisoners-of-war through the YMCA. In 1944, he became professor of Russian at Yale University, and in 1946, director of the Department of Russian Languages and Literatures at Connecticut College for Women.
Kazem-Bek accepted his last and somewhat dubious post after returning to his homeland, which had then become the Soviet Union. During the last twenty years of his life, he worked for the Moscow Patriarchate, the official church of Russia, in the area of public relations. While he was in the Soviet Union, the Soviet newspaper Pravda released a false article which connected Kazem-Bek with pro-Soviet work and hinted at his betrayal of the cause of the Russian Orthodox emigration. In response, Kazem-Bek demanded that his name be cleared, and threatened to commit suicide if the newspaper did not comply. In spite of these efforts, many of his friends and followers abroad remained unsure of his position and views, and especially of the nature of his work in the USSR.
Aleksandr Kazem-Bek died in the Soviet Union on February 21, 1977, and is buried near the Church of the Transfiguration near Moscow.
Scope and Content
The name of Aleksandr Kazem-Bek has several spelling variations. He is also documented as Alexander Kazem-Bek, Alexander Kazem-Beg, Alexandre Kasem-Beg, and Alexandre Kazem Beg. The version used for the purposes of this collection, Aleksandr Kazem-Bek, is according to the Library of Congress Authorities.
The bulk of the Kazem-Bek Papers consists of lecture notes, rough drafts, and manuscripts collected and written by Kazem-Bek in connection to his work as director of Connecticut College's Slavic Department and as a Russian historian. Also included is a number of personal documents relating to Kazem-Bek and his family, such as social security applicatons, copies of passports, emigration papers, inquiries concerning employment, bills and invoices, etc. Of additional note are family photographs and the personal and professional correspondence of Kazem-Bek and his family.
Included in these papers is a collection of Soviet and Russian émigré periodicals dated 1933-1956, as well as a series of Russian religious journals dated 1954-1958, to which Kazem-Bek regularly contributed as writer and editor. Several titles of the newspapers included are Novaia zaria, Novyi put', Mladorosskaia iskra, and Voskresenie Rossii. These newspapers vary in nature and content from the official publication of the Mladorossi, to a daily Russian émigré newspaper based in San Francisco. The religious journals, for which Kazem-Bek regularly wrote when he returned to the Soviet Union towards the end of his life, consist of The Journal of the Moscow Patriarchate (Zhurnal Moskovskoi Patriarkhii and One Church (Edinaia Tserkov')
The entire newspaper collection is found in three flat boxes and six oversize flat boxes (partially sorted and unfolded). There are also three flat boxes containing newspaper clippings and newspapers. One of these flat boxes contains a folder of oversize items referred to in the container list as Oversize Materials. Also present throughout the collection are several separation sheets to mark where oversize materials have been extracted and placed into the oversize boxes.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in eight series
Series I: Correspondence, 1930-1961
Series II: Writings
Subseries I.1: Manuscripts of prominent persons
Subseries II.2: Articles by Kazem-Bek
Subseries II.3: History of Russia, unpublished book by Kazem-Bek
Subseries II.4: History of the Russian Church, unpublished book by Kazem-Bek
Subseries II.5: The History of Russian Colonization, unpublished book by Kazem-Bek
Subseries II.6: Drafts of various articles, broadcasts, sermons, other writings
Subseries II.7: Articles by other authors
Series III: Documents
Series IV: Photographs
Series V: Printed Materials, 1928-1968
Subseries V.1: Various printed brochures, articles, biographies, publications, periodicals, journals, etc.
Subseries V.2: La Vie Intellectuelle, March 1947-February 1948
Subseries V.3: Religious journals, 1954-1968
Series VI: Subject Files, 1921-1965
Series VII: Clippings
Series VIII: Flat Boxes
Subseries VIII.1: Oversize materials
Subjects
Orthodox Church in America.; Mladorosskai︠a︡ partii︠a︡.; Avinoff, Andrey, 1884-1949.; Berdiaev, Nikolai, 1874-1948.; Muromt︠s︡eva-Bunina, V. N. (Vera Nikolaevna).; Dostoyevsky, Fyodor, 1821-1881.; Karpovich, Michael, 1888-1959.; Knupffer, George.; Konovalov, Aleksandr.; Likhachev, B. T.; Poole, D. C. (Dewitt Clinton), 1828-1917.; Sablin, Evgeniĭ Vasilʹevich, d. 1949.; Sedykh, Andreĭ, 1902-; Slonim, Marc, 1894-1976.; Sorokin, Pitirim Aleksandrovich, 1889-1968.; Timasheff, Nicholas S. (Nicholas Sergeyevitch), 1886-1970.; Vakar, Nicholas P. (Nicholas Platonovich), 1894-1970.; Azerbaijanis.; Expatriate authors--France--Paris.; Monarchy--Russia.; Religious thought--20th century.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
Consult with appropriate curator to access fragile newspaper series.
Acquisition
Svetlana Kasem-Beg Gift 1960s
This collection was given to the Bakhmeteff Archive in the early 1960's by Svetlana Kasem-Beg, the first wife of Aleksandr Kazem-Bek.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence with prominent persons, 1930-1955
    - Avinoff, Andrey. Bedford, Long Island, Pittsburgh, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
      (2 handwritten letters signed, also included 1 letter from Avinoff’s wife)
    - Bunina, Vera: see Muromtseva-Bunina
    - Karpovich, Michael. New London, CT, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      (2 typed letters signed with Kazem-Bek’s responses)
    - Knupffer, George. London, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      (3 typed letters signed, 1 envelope)
    - Konovalov, Aleksandr. 1940 August 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      (1 typed letter)
    - Likhachev, Boris. Paris, Monaco, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      (24 handwritten letters signed)
    - Moseley, Philip. New York, 1952 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      (1 typed letter signed, with Kazem-Bek’s response)
    - Muromtseva-Bunina, V. N. Paris, 1951 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (1 handwritten letter signed)
    - Poole, De Witt Clinton: see Series VI: Subject Files-- Memoranda and correspondence with U.S. War Department, 10, Folder 5 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Sablin, Evgenii. London, 1941 December 26 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Sedykh, Andrei. New York, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      (1 typed letter signed)
    - Slonim, Mark. New York, 1944 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Sorokin, Pitirim. Cambridge, MA, New London, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      handwritten letters signed, 1 typed letter signed, typed autobiography, list of publications)
    - Timasheff, Nicholas, 1930 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Vakar, Nicholas. Various places, 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      (15 handwritten letters signed and 3 typed letters. Also included 1 letter from Vakar’s wife)
  - General Correspondence, 1940-1961
    - Book dealers (Box 1, Folder 14)
      (invoices, bills, receipts, letters, notices of overdue payments, etc.)
    - Chronological correspondence
      - In English, 1945-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - In French, 1940-1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - In Russian
        - 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        - 1952-1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Churches and religious organizations, 1943-1954 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      (professional and personal correspondence with clerics and members of various religious organizations such as the Fellowship of Sts. Alban and Sergius, the World Council of Churches, etc.)
    - College students, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      (invitations, thank you notes, greeting cards, good wishes, etc.)
    - Family, 1941-1956 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      (letters and telegrams to Aleksandr Kazem-Bek from his first and second wives, Svetlana and Silva, his children, other family relations)
    - Novaia zaria newspaper, 1944-1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      (correspondence with editors and publishers, requests for submitted articles, etc.)
    - Outgoing correspondence, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Universities, 1944-1956 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      (Columbia, Harvard, Middlebury, Smith College, Yale, et al. Employment possibilities, invitations to conferences, lectures, and other events, both personal and official correspondence with professors, etc.)
- Series II: Writings
  - Subseries II.1: Manuscripts of Prominent Persons
    - Berdiaev, Nikolai: "Razdor mira i khristianstvo" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      (handwritten essay, text in Russian)
  - Subseries II.2: Articles by Kazem-Bek
    - Berdiaev (Box 2, Folder 2)
      (undated typed article "Berdiaev o tserkvi," various undated and untitled typed drafts)
    - Dostoyevsky (Box 2, Folder 3)
      (undated typed article "Gide and Dostoyevsky")
    - For Novaia zaria newspaper (Box 2, Folder 4)
      (various undated and untitled handwritten drafts, typed interview of Kazem-Bek)
    - "Problems in the Teaching of Russian:" see Series VI: Subject Files--Russian language programs and notes, 10, Folder 12 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - In French (undated typed articles)
      - "Le cas d'Anastace Vonsiatsky" (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - "Le Traite d'Alliance Anglo-Russe a Été Conclu il y a Un An" (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - "L'Evolution Politique de la France Depuis l'Armistice de 1940" (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - "Russie-Angleterre: Une Alliance en Depit des Polemes" (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Religious themes
      - In Russian (undated typed articles)
        - "Sbor episkopov s mirianami" (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - "S tserkoviu ili s Karlovtsami?" (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - "Karlovtsi vovremia i posle voiny" (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - "Tserkovsnoie zapreshchenie" (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - "Vselenskoie edinstvo pravoslaviia" (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - "Solidarnost' sester-tser'kvei s russkoi tserkoviiu" (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - "Loial'nost' grazhdan-khristian" (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - "Poslushanie i svoboda v tserkvi" (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - Articles 1-5 repeated with handwritten corrections (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - "Konets brestskoi unii" (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - "Podvig ravnoapostol'noi Niny" (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - "Religiia, kak stroi zhizni" (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - "Tserkov'" (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - "Tserkovnaia avtokefaliia?" (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - "Tserkovnyi sobor v Moskve" (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - "Zametka ob otnoshenii pravoslavnoi tserkvi k sotsial'nomu voprosu" (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - In French (undated typed and handwritten drafts) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Russia (undated typed articles)
      - "Rossiia i Iaponiia: Bor'ba za Sakhalin v proshlom i v nastoiashchem" (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - "Anglo-russkii soiuz" (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - "39 Years Ago...Russian Pearl Harbor" (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - "Russia and the Slavs" (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Varia (undated typed articles)
      - "Gadalki i zvezdochki" (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - "Chto god griadushchii nam gotovit?" (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - "O Germanii, kapitalisme i drugikh veshchakh" (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - "O fantasmagorii k deistvitel'nosti" (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - "Ne predvidenie, a propaganda!" (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subseries II.3: History of Russia, unpublished book by Kazem-Bek
    - Draft 1 (undated typed chapters)
      - Zakat Vizantii i vozvyshenie Moskvy (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Tretii Rim (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Na strazhe Evropy (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Narod - hoziaiin prostranstva (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Pereneseniie moshchei sviatitelia (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Vseia Rossii chudotvorets (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Zakat viz (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Mezhdu papoi i sultanom (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Draft 2 (handwritten notes) (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Draft 3: typed chapters and notes from a book on the Russian Revolution
      - Narodnyi komissariiat po delam natsional'nostei (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Perviye gody Sovetskoi Federatsyi (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Revolutsiia pered dilemoi posle provala stavki na internatsional (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Draft 4: handwritten notes, undated typed chapters
      - Dekabristy (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Istoriia orfografii v Rossii (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Rozhdestvo v Kremle: 25oe Dekabria 1648 goda (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Notes (Box 3, Folder 3)
      (handwritten, undated)
  - Subseries II.4: History of the Russian Church, unpublished book by Kazem-Bek
    - Draft: Handwritten Chapters
      - Khristianstvo, kak put' k velikoderzhavnosti (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Pervaia kanonizatsiia v russkoi tserkvi (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Pravoslavie v Novgorodskoi Rusi (1949) (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Pravoslavie i russkaia kultura (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Russkoie pravoslavie - pravoslavnaia Rus' (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Notes (Box 3, Folder 5)
      (undated, handwritten)
  - Subseries II.5: The History of Russian Colonization, unpublished book by Kazem-Bek (drafts, notes, chapter divisions, relevant material)
    - Asia (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - The Baltics (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Bibliography (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Central Asia (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Crimea, the Black Sea (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Draft (Box 3, Folder 11)
      (overview of book, bibliography)
    - Finland (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Georgia, Armenia (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Kazakhstan (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Kazaks (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Kyrgystan (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Krainii sever (far north) (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Malaia Rus', Ukraine (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Northern Caucasus (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Povolzh'e (Volga region) (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Puti Rossii (Ways of Russia) (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Revolution and the National Question" essay (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Russia and the East (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Siberia and the Far East (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Tajikistan (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Tatars, Bashkiria (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Turkmenistan (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Uzbekistan (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Subseries II.6: Drafts of various articles, broadcasts, sermons, other writings)
    - Chapters from the novel XX Century (Box 4, Folder 5)
      (undated typed drafts and handwritten notes)
    - For the coordinator of information on radio broadcasts to the USSR
      (typed drafts)
      - "Memorandum on Radio Broadcasts in the Russian Language to the Soviet Union" (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - "Why Russia Does not Have a Fifth Column" (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - "Les Russes aux États-Unis: Étude pour le Coordinator of Information" (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Propagation of Christianity in the Russian Arctic (Box 4, Folder 7)
      (undated typed text)
    - Russian Imperial Family (Box 4, Folder 8)
      (clippings, undated typed text)
    - Russian work of the YMCA in the USA (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Sermons, 1945-1948
      (typed and handwritten drafts)
      - "Slovo o edinoi, sviatoi, sobornoi i apostol'skoi tserkvi" (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Ukrainian emigration, 9 January 1942
      (typed texts)
      - "Memorandum on the Ukrainian Emigration" (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - "Ukrainskaia emigratsiia" (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - War themes
      (undated typed texts)
      - "35 let tomu nazad...i teper'" (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - "O mobilizatsii amerikanskoi demokratii dlia total'noi voiny" (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - "1946 - pervyi poslevoiennyi god" (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Subseries II.7: Articles by other authors
    - Canan, Bromley: "He Came Too Soon, This Christ" (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Likhachev, Boris: "Quelques Reflexions sur des Themes Monarchiques" (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Poole, de Witt Clinton: "Russia and the United States" (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Presniakov, Aleksandr: "Nash tserkovnyi vopros," 1906 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Sergeev, Archbishop Aleksii: "Sviatyie patrioty" (Box 4, Folder 17)
      (handwritten draft)
    - Vakar, Nikolai: "Rossiia: Slavianam" (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Woodhouse, C.M.: "Dostoyevsky as Prophet" (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Unidentified (Box 4, Folder 20)
      (various texts, including a handwritten biography of Patriarch Meletios and the typed text of "Memorandum Regarding the Article Entitled 'The Mission of Christianity in the Modern World' by A. KrasheninnikofPublished in the Journal of the Moscow Patriarchate, No. 6, 1949")
- Series III: Documents
  - Kazem-Bek’s family documents (Box 4, Folder 21)
    (immigration papers, visas, passports, resumés, Aleksandr Kazem-Bek biographical statement, family correspondence, etc.)
  - Kazem-Bek in the USSR, 1956-1977 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    (correspondence with Svetlana Kazem-Bek, obituaries, etc.)
  - Kazem-Bek's personal documents (Box 4, Folder 23)
    (governmental awards, business cards, royal decrees, Kazem-Bek family name records, social security, etc.)
- Series IV: Photographs
  - Official photographs (Box 5, Folder 1)
    (undated movie stills from Ivan the Terrible and undated photographs of the Pageant of Russia)
  - Personal photographs (Box 5, Folder 2)
    (friends and family, students from Connecticut College, faces and activities of the Mladoross movement, the Royal Family, the Russian Orthodox Patriarch, photographs of paintings by Kazem-Bek. Fifty-two black and write photographs and eight color photographs. Notable names include: Grand Duke Kirill Vladimirovich Romanov, Grand Duchess Victoria Romanova, Grand Duke Andrei Vladimirovich Romanov, Patriarch Aleksii of Moscow and All Russia, Alexander Gretchaninoff, Lev Aleksandrovich Kazem-Bek and Nadezhda Kazem-Bek (Aleksandr L'vovich's parents). Also portrayed are main members of the Mladorossi: Pantaleon Avseniev, Serge Boulatzel, Gregory Boutakov, Count Igor Caruso, Prince Mikhail Chavchavadze, Kirill Chevich, Boris Demidov, Helen Didriks, Harold Graf, Anatolii Karamosko, Prince Vladimir Krassinskii, Andrei Nekrasov, George Otvinovskii, Serge Otvinovskii, Alexander Ougrimov, Anatolii Steiger, Platon Stephanovich, Maximilian Strenger, Pierre Vassiliev, Kirill Wilezhkovskii, Serge Zbychevskii. One especially notable photograph portrays Aleksandr Kazem-Bek as a child, with his parents and officers from the aboard the frigate Pallada.
- Series V: Printed Materials, 1928-1968
  - Subseries V.1: Various printed brochures, articles, biographies, publications, periodicals, journals, etc.
    - Bulletin Mladoross 1, February 1930-April 1931 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Bulletin Mladoross 2, May 1931-January 1932 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Cahiers de la Nouvelle Époque: Problèmes du Monde Nouveau Occident et Russie, No. 2. Paris 1945 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Edinaia tserkov' undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
      (excerpts which include an article written by Kazem-Bek entitled "Prepodobnyi Makarii Egipetskii")
    - Information Bulletin, Washington, D.C., 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - L'Education Nationale, Paris, March-April 1952 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Losskii, H.: Dialekticheskii materialism v SSSR, Paris 1934 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Mladoross party booklets 1, 1928-1933
      (printed booklets)
      - "K Molodoi Rossii: sbornik Mladorossov" (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Young Russia (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Mladoross party booklets
      (2 printed booklets)
      - Elita-Vil'chkovskii, Kirill
        - "O Mladorosskoi ideologii" (Box 5, Folder 11)
        - "O natsional'noi revoliutsii" (Box 5, Folder 11)
        - Lishin, N: "Paralleli" (Box 5, Folder 11)
        - "Pamiatka Mladorossa" (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Na pamiat' iz Pochaevskoi Lavry (Box 5, Folder 12)
      (undated printed booklet)
    - Nezavisimyi golos journal, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      (various undated scraps in poor condition)
    - Novosti Tolstovskogo Fonda periodical, New York, May 1951 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Objets de Vertu, New York 1952 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      (catalog of a public exhibition which included the works of Carl Fabergé, jewels, and icons, with an inscription)
    - Oswiecim Camp of Death, New York 1944 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      (printed booklet)
    - Publications of Roman Jacobson, 1951-1952
      - A Bibliography of the Publications of Roman Jacobson on Language, Literature, and Culture (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - The Archetype of the First Edition of the Igor Tale (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Religious
      (printed booklets and newspapers)
      - Kartashev, A.V.: Vetkhozavetnaia bibleiskaia kritika, Paris 1947 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Khronika zhizhni russkoi pravoslavnoi tserkvi v zapadnoi Evrope, Paris (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Polozhenie upravlenii russkoi pravoslavnoi tserkvi, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Pravoslavnaia Rus', Jordanville, NY, April 1948 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Messager de l'Exarchat du Patriarche Russe en Europe Occidentale, December 1955 (Box 6, Folder 6)